Guide to the Ninfa Rodriguez Laurenzo Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Ninfa Rodriguez Laurenzo Papers
1971-2004
2008-008
Laurenzo, Ninfa
9.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Ninfa’s Papers include business plans, business, personal, and political correspondence, photographs, magazine and newspaper clippings press coverage, proof of public service deeds, scrapbooks, artifacts (buttons and stamps, memorabilia, menus, plaques), and framed enlarged picture and media items and roughly cover the years from 1971 to 2001.
Biographical Information:
In 1969, Ninfa’s husband died suddenly, and she was left to raise five children. Ninfa mortgaged her house and opened a little taqueria on the site of the tortilla factory. In 1973, she opened a ten-table restaurant, serving her mother’s recipes and adding her own. With money from a friend in Mexico, Ninfa soon opened a second dining room and later pushed out a wall to expand again. Within ten years, the single restaurant expanded into a multi-million dollar business with nine restaurants in Houston and one in Dallas. In 1985, Ninfa employed 800-1000 people and served about two million people per year. Some believe that Ninfa Laurenzo laid the foundation for the Mexican restaurant industry in Houston.
Ninfa’s restaurants were so successful that expansion came fast and led to excessive debt. Restaurants opened too quickly and without reliable store managers. In 1985, Ninfa, USA became a subsidiary of McFaddin, which employed her sons as executives. Ninfa remained with Ninfa’s Inc. That arrangement did not last. By 1997, an Austin restaurant chain bought the company to pull it out of bankruptcy.
With her success, Ninfa gave back to the community with nonprofit service. She served on the boards of the Gulf Coast Regional Blood Center, Houston Community College System, Houston Metropolitan Transit Authority and Houston Hispanic Forum. She received many rewards as well, the U.S. Hispanic Chamber of Commerce’s Business Recognition Award, for example. In 1984, Vice-President George Bush appointed Ninfa to be one of five goodwill ambassadors to welcome Pope John Paul II to Puerto Rico. In 1996, Ninfa Laurenzo was named one of eight Legends of Texas along with Walter Cronkite and Barbara Jordan, for their impact on Texas and their local communities. Ninfa was inducted into the Texas Women’s Hall of Fame in 1998, and Theater under the Stars made her life into a musical.
Ninfa Laurenzo represented her community politically as well. In 1988, Ninfa seconded George H. W. Bush’s nomination for president in the Republican Convention in New Orleans. In 1992, Ninfa was co-chair of the hospitality committee for the Republican Convention in Houston where she opened the convention with a speech in both English and Spanish, and she led the delegates in the Pledge of Allegiance.
Through marriage, the Laurenzo family is tied to both the Mandolas and Carrabas. At the opening of a new restaurant, one of Ninfa’s sons, Tom Laurenzo said, “We have a story to tell about a woman who is a great cook and about her family that followed her into the business.” Ninfa Laurenzo died in 2001, but her restaurants and her children’s restaurants continue as landmarks in Houston’s cultural history.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Advertisements; Newspapers; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Topical Term:
Business planning -- Restaurants; Mexican American cooking; Mexican Americans -- Study and teaching
Acquisition Information:
Donated by Phyllis Mandola
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Scope and Contents
Ninfa’s Papers include business plans, business, personal, and political correspondence, photographs, magazine and newspaper clippings press coverage, proof of public service deeds, scrapbooks, artifacts (buttons and stamps, memorabilia, menus, plaques), and framed enlarged picture and media items and roughly cover the years from 1971 to 2001.
Detailed List of Contents
- Biographical, undated
  - Personal and Business Biographies, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Business Plans and Training, 1977-2000
  - Trust/Insurance Documents, 1977-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Prospectus, Plans, and Company Profiles, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rio Star Corporation Business Plan and Stock, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ninfa’s Price List and Balance Sheet, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bambolino’s Business Plan, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Career Development Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ninfa Training Handbook, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1986-2001
  - Business, 1986-2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal, 1986-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal Contacts, 1988-2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Washington D.C. - Political, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Photographs, 1971-1999
  - Ninfa’s Friends- Photo Greetings, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Restaurant, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ninfa’s Friends- Bar Mitzvah 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - New Year’s Eve, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ninfa’s Anniversary Party, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Texas Association of Mexican-American Chambers of Commerce (TAMACC) Convention, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bambolino's, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - In the Park, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Little League Parade, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Thanksgiving Day Party and Catering, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - USA Treasurer’s: Visit to Ninfa’s at Navigation, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ninfa’s Tenth 10th Anniversary at Westheimer, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Town and Country, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bambolino’s Unit, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Inside Restaurants, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Ninfa’s Kirby Customers, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Houston International Festival, Houston Library Plaza, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Contest Winners at Ninfa’s West,Santos Family and Ninfa, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Trip Winner’s at Ninfa’s West,Girl Scout Cookie Show at Dillard’s, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Joey Jack Seafood Grand Opening, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Ninfa, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Texas Women Hall of Fame Award Ceremony, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - George Herbert Walker Bush Inauguration, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Hernandez Open House, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Christmas Party at Ninfa’s, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Ninfa Birthday Party with Photos and Guest List, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Arthritis Award, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ninfa’s Cuisines, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - George Herbert Walker Bush Republican Convention, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Family and Baptism, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - NASA, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - At Ninfaritas, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Travel, 1995-1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ninfa’s Friends, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Ninfa Media Coverage, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ninfa and Restaurant Signs, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ninfa Restaurant Parade, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Restaurant Black Tie Event, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ninfa at Bambolino’s West Chase, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bambolino’s, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Awards and Ceremonies, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Family and Friends, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ushuaia, Tierra del Fuego, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Buenos Aries Cathedral, Boca and Recoleta Cathedral, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Ninfa’s Restaurant, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Laurenzo’s, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Ninfa at Channel 2 Muscular Dystrophy Awards (MDA) Awards, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Laurenzo’s Pasta and Sea Food, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Ninfa’s Restaurant Signs, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Grand Opening of Ninfa’s at Old Spanish Trail, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Restaurant Gatherings, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Social Gathering, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Bellaire Gracias Opening, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Ninfa at Navigation, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Ninfa at Foley’s Cooking Fiesta, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Ninfa at a Clown Celebration, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ninfa at Atchafalaya Restaurant, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Ninfa with Phil Gramm, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Strake for Lt. Governor, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Ninfa in a Parade, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Party at Ninfa’s Cantina, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Ninfa’s Restaurant Opening, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Puerto Madryn, Puerto Roma Sea Lions, Welsh Tea House,Montevideo, Buenos Aries, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Buenos Aries, Argentina, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - A Party at Westheimer, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Party in Puerto Varas, Chile, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Ninfa’s Cuisines, undated (Box 2, Folder 42-46)
- Press Coverage
  - News Kits, 1980-1988
    - Bambolino’s, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Bambolino’s, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Ninfa Restaurant, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Magazines, 1986-1994
    - Houston City Magazine, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Houston Gourmet Cooks Magazine - Cookbook, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Houston Gourmet, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Houston Gourmet, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Profiles - Special Collector’s Issue, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Houston Gourmet, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Public Service, 1986-2004
  - Event Programs, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Event Programs, 1989-2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Economic Summit, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Speeches, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Speeches, 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Cancer Contributions, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Community Affiliations List, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Award Certificates, 1991-2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - YMCA, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Check Donations, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Holocaust, Galveston-Houston & Lion’s Bank, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Gulf Blood Bank, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Gulf Blood Bank, 1999-2001 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - University of St.Thomas Letter of Appreciation, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Laurenzo Early Childhood Center, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Artifacts, 1978-2003
  - Ephemera, 2003
    - Mural Dedication Ceremony, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Buttons and Stamps, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Advertising Specialties 1, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Advertising Specialties 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Friendship Sentiments, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Ninfa Theatre Under The Stars (TUTS) Script, 1988/1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Ninfa Gift Certificates, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Menus, 1985-1986
    - Child and Regular Menus, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Laurenzo’s Italian Bar & Grill Menu and Photos, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Ninfa Menus, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Ninfa Menu Lunch Specials, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Ninfa Restaurant Menu Covers, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Ninfa’s Mexican Restaurant Menus- Clearwater, Florida, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Ninfa’s Mexican Restaurant Menus- Houston, Texas, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Plaques, 1978-1997
    - A Chicana Salute to Ninfa from the Chicana Caucus, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Texas Mexican- American Business Hall of Fame, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Ninfa’s E.E.I Excellence Award, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Ninfa’s Big Brothers and Sisters of Houston President’s Award, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Ninfa Grand Marshall of 1987 Parade Award (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Houston Young Lawyers Association Liberty Bell Award, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Ninfa Honorary 1st Degree Black Belt, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Entrepreneur of the Year Finalist, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - South Houston Spanish Club Support Award, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Ninfa’s MexStudies Generous Support Award @ UH, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Boy Scouts and Roland Laurenzo as Chairman, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Ninfa’s Guardian Member Award for Boy Scouts, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Leadership Member Award- Ninfa of Boy Scouts, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - University of Houston- Downtown College- Professor for a Day Award, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Scrapbooks, 1979-1990
  - Dutch Fiesta, 1979-1990 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - George Herbert Walker Bush souvenirs, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Oversized, 1975-2004
  - Photographs, 1988-1992
    - Ninfa, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Family, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1975-2004
    - Biographical, 1975-2001 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Restaurant Reviews, 1987-2004 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Political Coverage, 1988-1992 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbooks, 1976-1990
    - Metro - In Appreciation, 1976-1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Random Restaurant Media, 1979-1990 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Restaurant Unit #5, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Ninfa Restaurant Media, 1975-1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Ninfa Restaurant Media, 1981-1989 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Houston Gracias Positives, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Magazines, 1985
    - Ninfa’s Cantina at Foley’s, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Framed Items (shelved), 1976-1994
    - Ninfa Laurenzo, Kaye Marvins- Houston, Photograph of Self, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Jim McConn Ninfa Laurenzo Proclamation Award, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Outstanding Business Woman Award HouMex Chamber of Commerce, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Ninfa’s Thank You Award from George Herbert Walker Bush, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Maria Laurenzo Riostar Corporation Success Magazine Article, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - The Houston Post, Business Houston, Christmas in July, Newpaperthon with Ninfa Laurenzo, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Winter Ball Honors 10 Women: Houston Post Style Section, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Bob Lanier Houston Mayor’s Proclamation of Ninfa Laurenzo Day, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Distinguished Member for Hispanic Boy Scouting, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Ninfa’s New Cantina- An Inside Restaurant Advertisements, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Certificate of Appreciation from the American Cancer Society, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)